the circulating levels of DHT in
response to testosterone therapy do not
correlate with those found in Androgen
sensitive tissues like the prostate and
skin for
example all right so you know so Stephen
you're a
dermatologist and uh a great one by the
way but so that transdermal cream
there's a lot of confusion when it comes
to DHT levels did you not agree exactly
yes that that's one of the comments I
see under the videos most of the time um
well doc you're bold and that's probably
because of the high DHT levels I was
bold before TRC of course but that's the
that's the commments right well well so
so you can correct me and any thing that
we're about to talk about of course
because you're a brilliant mind is a
scientist yourself so look so let's talk
about the normal range for DHC for
instance at Lab Core which is our most
popular lab over here really is is 30 to
85 nanograms to deciliter now I hope men
understand that no matter what method of
delivery you get for t testosterone it's
going to raise DHT when you raise levels
of testosterone free testosterone you're
going to raise levels of DHT that's how
testosterone Works testosterone Works
through its active metabolites that's
why they're called active metabolites it
does every most men out there don't
really think about the physiology of
testosterone they just think the more
testosterone the better not
understanding that testosterone when it
reaches many of the target tissues has
to be converted into its active
metabolites to give you the benefits of
testosterone all right so when you
compare the serum DHT levels between
injections and transdermal Delivery
Systems there is a significant increase
in serum levels of DHT with the Trans
dermals and this is of course due to the
high concentration of five Alpha
reductase enzymes in the
skin but now when it comes to measuring
levels of DHT it's important to
understand that the circulating levels
of DHT in response to testosterone
therapy do not correlate with those
found in Androgen sensitive tissues like
the prostate and skin for example now
this is due to the local regulatory
mechanisms that tightly control
intracellular Andrian homeostasis
intracellular concentrations of DHT are
independent of circulating levels of DHT
DHT Works in a paracrine fashion and is
made in the Target tissues so even
though you significantly raise DHT in a
transdermal delivery system it has no
effect on the intracellular
levels so you just mentioned hair loss
so one of the most common side effects
of testost therapy is of course hair
loss not only occurs in those with a
genetic predisposition as it did in you
but it's still one of the most common
side effects now any method of delivery
that increases free testosterone
increases DHT can cause hair loss in
those that are susceptible we all know
that but men think that a transdermal
method raises the DHD levels higher
therefore it must cause more hair loss
well that increase in serum DHT is not
the mechanism of how it causes hair loss
loss it's the free testosterone that
enters the hair follicle where it is
converted into DHT which will cause hair
loss and not the circulating levels of
DHT and people need to remember there's
only a limited number of andine
receptors for the DHT to bind to and
once those receptors are fully saturated
raising DHT any further will have no
effect so if a man's DHT receptors for
instance are fully saturated DHT level
of 70 then raising it three or four
times that will have no further effect
on hair loss because it can't exert an
effect there's no receptor to bind
to it's important to know also that
those receptors are also fully saturated
at a fairly low testosterone level in
fact in the prostate it's 250 nanograms
per deciliter anything above that has no
effect on prostate tissue because the
angine receptors are fully
saturated now I actually can think of
maybe one or some instances where the
transdermals will cause more hair loss
than the injections now we've already
discussed that the transdermals can
raise free testosterone levels better
than the in injections for any given
total in the same man therefore if you
have a more free testosterone you have
more testosterone to be converted into
DHD at the cellular level now if you
didn't get a high level of free
testosterone injections and weren't
doing it daily well then trans dermals
is going to raise your free testosterone
levels better they're going to be
consistently elevated and it can
saturate your receptors and cause more
hair loss in that instance but it's once
again related to the level of free
testosterone all
right but if you raise free testosterone
to the same level on injections as you
do on cream and you have a stable level
of free testosterone such as that with
daily injections then you will have an
equal amount of hair loss now the
takeaway messes it's not the serum DHT
levels exerting the effects but instead
the intra cellular levels of DHT from
the free testosterone so you'll see guys
you know trying to manipulate their DHT
Levels by applying the the the you know
the cream to the scrotum and then some
on the you know upper inner arm or top
of their foot behind their knee because
I want to lower that DHD they need to
understand it has it's not going to have
any effect on your hair loss it'll have
an effect on your free testosterone
potentially but not hair loss we've
already also established you can apply
the cream anywhere that you have skin
from head to toe nothing it's just the
scrotal skin for two reasons better
levels and most denes reduce risk of
transference all right so the your
listeners are then going to be asking
this I'm sure well then why do five
Alpha reduct taste Inhibitors like
Propecia work for hair loss Dr nichels I
mean they lower serum DHT levels and
that has to be the mechanism you're just
wrong well understand that the
effectiveness of those five Alpha
reductase inhibitor resides at the level
of the haed follicle lowered follicular
concentrations of DHT not a reduction of
circulating DHT because that's not been
shown to correlate with male androgenic
alopecia well how do we know this well
Stephen this is why we're all scientists
that we have to look at medical
studies so in 2010 there was a study
published in the animals of internal
medicine they you know gave men
transdermal DHT all right now these men
were exposed to exceptionally high
levels of DHT in response to a daily
application of DHT for 24 months two
years their DHT levels exceeded 700
nagram per deciliter and some even over
a thousand which is over 10 times the
normal range and what they found was
that the DHT was not associated with
acne male androgenic alpia or other
Androgen Associated Skin Pathology right
so just like with estral when you take a
medication and lower serum DHT levels
you lower levels at the cellular level
and therefore lose the beneficial
effects of DHT on those tissues and this
is of course the cause of the
post-finasteride syndrome which includes
persistent sexual neuros psychiatric and
physical symptoms so that's why we don't
want to block the active metabolites of
testosterone because we're going to pay
a price in other tissues in other areas
we may protect our hair but we'll pay a
price somewhere else so that's the
that's kind of the the the
misconceptions of about
DHT and that uh so those serum levels
really don't mean anything okay they
they don't mean anything and that's why
I point out the men that look if you go
to any Forum where the majority of men
on those forums are injecting and what
are they complaining about the major
complaints are going to be acne and hair
loss and yet they're injecting so you
don't have to raise DHT a lot to get
hair loss but when we go to creams and
we're raising that free testosterone
levels and consistently raising it with
that nice little sine wave you can have
a little more hair loss than a man that
didn't get adequate consistent pre
testosterone levels on the injections
all right so I hope I explain that a
little bit uh to where it's
understandable you're a dermatologist so
tell me if there's anything that we kind
of missed in there or that we can add to
it yeah perfectly perfectly Keith but um
I guess some
bio availability um in between there's
in between people there's difference one
will absorb better on the scrotal skin
than the other still of course but I
guess in all studies has been shown
absorption on genital skin is eight
times higher than on whatever skin in
the same individual so um I guess you're
right it's the best spot to apply it um
next to the benefits on the transference
of course well well it's close as close
as we can almost get to a mucous
membrane almost because it's so thin
skin and Holly vascu that's just really
all there is to it but look before we
started using the scrotal skin all right
20 years ago
we got I got good levels applying it to
the you know skin of the the the upper
shoulder neck you know upper pectoral
region you know as long as it's a
hairless region you can get good levels
but you just got consistently good
levels and you got levels utilizing less
cream by going to scrotal skin and once
again the incidence of transference
drops dramatically when somebody applies
to the neck upper shoulder upper chest
read you got to remember if you're
holding a baby if your wife sleeps you
know they lay down to watch a movie
together and they're they're exposed to
that face to your skin there you're
going to have some issues of
transference there's really a lot of
times not a lot of direct skin-to-skin
contact with that scrotal skin I mean
you know and some guys are say oh yeah
well you know I apply my white flats to
go down and do certain things well look
that's when I talked about earlier it's
a mature population of men we've told
you how to avoid transference if if
you're going to apply it and 30 minutes
later your your wife or girlfriend's
gonna go do that go wash it off okay
just go wash it off or don't if you know
that's going to happen don't apply it
and uh and and then apply it afterwards
all
[Music]
right